<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Account of what passed at the execution of Sir Will. Parkyns and Sir John Friend, at Tyburn on Friday, April 3d., 1696</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B16647</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">8435412</idno>
  <idno type="VID">204257</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248505027</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing A432</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">08435412</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B16647)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 204257)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1245:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Account of what passed at the execution of Sir Will. Parkyns and Sir John Friend, at Tyburn on Friday, April 3d., 1696</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Baldwin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Parkyns, William, --  Sir, 1649?-1696.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Friend, John, --  Sir, d. 1696.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:204257:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:204257:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:204257:2"/>
            <head>AN ACCOUNT Of what passed at the EXECUTION OF Sir Will. Parkyns, and Sir Joh. Friend, At <hi>Tyburn,</hi> on <hi>Friday, April</hi> 3d. 1696.</head>
            <p>THE Prisoners being drawn in a Sledge from <hi>Newgate</hi> to the Place of Execution, were permitted to have the Assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of Three Ministers of their own Chusing; <hi>Viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Collyer,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cook,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Snet.</hi>
            </p>
            <stage>Sir <hi>W. Parkyns</hi> came first up into the Cart, and had some private Discourse with one of the Ministers.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sir <hi>W. Parkyns.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>When must I deliver my Paper?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Minister.</speaker>
               <p>When all is over.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Then the Executioner went to put the Rope about Sir <hi>W. Parkyn</hi>'s Neck.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sir <hi>W. Parkyns.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>May not I Pray before it be put on?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Executioner.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, Sir if you please.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Then Sir <hi>J. Friend</hi> came into the Cart; and the Ministers and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soners all kneeling down, Mr. <hi>Cook</hi> read some Prayers out of the Morning-Prayer, and the Office for Visitation of the Sick: And then the Ministers standing up, ask'd them whether they were in Charity with all the World? And if they had offended any, whether they did ask them forgiveness? And whether they did desire the Absolution of the Church? Upon their Answer that they did, they laid their Hands upon their Heads, and Mr. <hi>Cook</hi> pronounced the Absolution, which ended in these words: <hi>And by His Authority committed to me, I absolve thee from all thy Sins, In the Name of the Father,</hi> &amp;c.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sir <hi>W. Parkyns.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>When are we to deliver our Papers?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Minister.</speaker>
               <p>Now, if you please.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>Sheriff.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Take what time you please, Sir, for your Devotions, we will wait your leisure.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Then the Two Prisoners continued in their private Prayers, Sir <hi>W. Parkyns</hi> making use of the Prayers in the <hi>Whole Duty of Man,</hi> and Sir <hi>J. Friend</hi> read some Prayers out of a Written Paper; and afterwards Sir <hi>W. Prakyns</hi> delivered to the Sheriffs a Paper.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>Sheriff.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>If you require any more time, you shall have it. You say this is your Paper?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sir <hi>Will. Parkyns,</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Yes Sir, and I desire you to dispose of it as you think sit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:204257:3"/>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>Sheriff.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Have you any thing to say, by way of Confession or Denial, of the Fact for which ye came hithe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to Suffer?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sir <hi>Will. Parkyns.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>What I think fit to say, is contained in that Paper.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>Sheriff.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>If you desire more time, you may have it; you shall have your Liberty.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Then Sir <hi>J. Friend</hi> held a Paper up.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>Sheriff.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>What do you say, Sir <hi>John?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sir <hi>J. Friend.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Sir, Here is a Paper, I desire it may be Printed: For I came here to Dye, and not to make a Speech; but to dye, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign my self to God; and I desire it may be Printed for all People to see it. And I have no more to say, but to beg of God to receive my Soul; I resign my Soul to him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>Sheriff.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>The Lord have Mercy upon you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sir <hi>J. Friend.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>I hope the Lord will have Mercy on me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>Sheriff.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Sir <hi>John,</hi> If you desire any more time, you shall have it; we will wait on you with great willingness.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sir <hi>J. Friend.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>I thank you Sir. Mr. <hi>Sheriff,</hi> I desire the Cart may not be too hasty to go away, till we give a sign.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>Sheriff.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>You shall have your own time; take your time, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate you own Sign, and the Cart shall not go before.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Then the Ropes were tyed about them.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sir <hi>J. Friend.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>I have no Animosity against any Man, I freely for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give all, and I hope God for Christ's sake will forgive me.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Then their Caps were put on.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sir <hi>J. Friend.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>My Saviour had a Crown of Thorns for me; the Lord receive my Soul, The Lord have Mercy upon me.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Then the Executioner askt them both forgiveness; and they answer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, We freely forgive you.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sir <hi>J. Friend.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Will not the things lye in my way?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Executioner.</speaker>
               <p>I will remove them. If you please, tell me when I may pull your Caps over your Eyes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Prisoners.</speaker>
               <p>When you will.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sir <hi>Will. Parkyns.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>The Lord receive my Spirit. Executioner, had I best hold up my Legs, or stand in the Cart when it goes away?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Executioner.</speaker>
               <p>It is best to stand, Sir, I think.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sir <hi>Will. Parkyns.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>But then my Feet will hang in the Cart.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Executioner.</speaker>
               <p>If you please, give me notice when you will have the Cart go away.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sir J. Friend.</speaker>
               <p>Stretch forth thy Arms, O Lord, and receive my Soul! O Lord, for thy Son's sake receive my Soul, and carry it into Heaven, I beseech thee. Executioner, when we knock, go away.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>And after a few Ejaculations, they gave the Sign, and the Cart drew away.</stage>
            <stage>They both of them gave Money to the Executioner; and having hung above half an hour, being a considerable time after they were dead, they were cut down and quartered according to the Sentence.</stage>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Baldwin,</hi> near the <hi>Oxford Arms</hi> in <hi>Warwicklane.</hi> 1696.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>